WHAT IS MATH AND WHY IS IT INCOMPLETE? Speaking very
generally, mathematicians try to describe certain mathematical objects. And make
claims about their structure and relation to other mathematical objects.
For much of human history this was grounded in geometry,
where proofs were grounded in geometric intuition.
As time went on, math became more abstract
and allowed us to describe more complicated and
abstract structures moving us further from our intuitions.
But what do we mean by describe a mathematical object? What is
the precise definition of a mathematical object? Which objects are considered to
be part of the mathematical universe, and which are not?
To understand these questions we will have
to understand the basics of mathematical logic.