First we fix our formal language L. It was Frege in
the 1800's who realized that the act of doing mathematics simply
involves the manipulations of the following sets of symbols:
Constant symbols, which represent special elements of a given structure like
0, 1, e, pi or the root of some tree.
Function symbols, such as successor, addition, multiplication.
Relation symbols, such as less than or in.
Variables, quantifiers, and brackets.
The boolean connectives,
of negation,
conjunctions,
disjunction
and implication.
The Boolean connectives can be represented
by truth tables or logic gates.
Note that in classical logic, a implies b is equivalent to not a or b.
This is not the case in intuitionistic logic for example.
But for this video we will stick to classical logic,
and soon I will make a video on non-classical logics
and they give rise to different mathematical universes.
We can divide these symbols into two groups, the logical
and non-logical symbols. The logical symbols are common to all
first order theories, and so proofs only involving the logical
symbols apply to all possible first-order structures. The non-logical symbols
are specific to a given theory,
for example if we are working with the theory of arithmetic, we
only need the constant 0, the successor function, and the addition function.
Whereas, if we work with the theory of graphs, we
only need a single binary relation E, where aEb means
that there is an edge between a and b.