First order logic is an expansion of propositional logic, where we
add variables and quantifiers to our set of logical symbols.
We also add certain constant, function and relation
symbols, which are specific to a given theory.
For example, if we want to study the natural numbers, we add the
constant 0, the successor function S, which just maps n to n plus
1, the addition and multiplication function, and the less than relation.
But if we want to study graphs, all we would need
is a single binary relation E expressing an edge between nodes.
These symbols which are specific to a
given theory are called the non-logical symbols,
and these are the logical symbols.
If we restrict ourselves to the logical symbols, then
we are in the domain of pure logic, and
whatever we prove applies to all first order structures.
The syntax of first order logic is
given by the so-called logical axioms.
We note that we have just added three
axioms to the axioms of propositional logic...
which determine how the forall quantifiers work. Note that since exists x P
x, where P is some arbitrary property like being even, is equivalent to
not forall x not P x. If there is an even number, then
we know that not all numbers are odd, so this is why we
technically only need to add the forall quantifier to the language.
One can show that this set of axioms is once again
sound and complete, but this time for first order logic, and
we will see this proof in the fourth video.
Often the equality relation is taken to be a logical symbol. In
this case, we need to add the following five axioms to our
list of logical axioms which define the behaviour of the equality symbol.
These axioms are hard to argue against, everything is equal to itself, if a
is equal to b then b is also equal to a, and so on.
Now we are ready to move to the semantics of
FOL. Again we fix our language, which again means we
pick a set of constant, function and relations symbols...
and we can define a structure,
which is represented by this fancy M, and
is equal to this tuple of elements.
This is the domain or universe of the structure...
and these are the 'interpretations' of the symbols in the language.
Constants are interpreted as specific elements in the structure...
and functions and relations are interpreted as subsets
of tuples of elements of the structures.
This is a bit abstract, so lets consider the example of the
standard structure of arithmetic, which is essentially just a number line.
Again we work within the language of arithmetic.
So, the universe is the set of natural numbers.
We can visualize this structure as a the number line,
and as we would expect, the interpretation of 0 is
just the first element in the number line.
The interpretations of the relations and functions are harder to visualize. But
formally we interpret the less than symbol as the set of all
pairs of natural numbers (x,y) such that x is less than y.
The successor function will map to the set of all pairs of
numbers such that the second is one greater than the first.
Similarly for the addition function, it maps to the set of
all triples (x,y,z) such that x plus y equals z.
So in general the interpretation function s is the bridge between
syntax and semantics, where s is a function which maps symbols
in a formal language, either to elements, or subsets of tuples
of elements of the domain of the structure.
This is a strange and abstract idea, to get a better understanding,
let us move to perhaps the simplest theory, the theory of graphs.
The language has a single binary relation E, and models are arbitrary sets
of points, which may or may not be connected by an arrow.
Where given nodes a and b, a E b if and
only if there is an arrow from a to b.