The syntax is the set's of formulas themselves,
and they are governed by a formal calculus
The semantics is the interpretation of these symbols.
Truth in the syntactical side is given by a valid
proof in a deductive calculus. Here Sigma proves phi means
that there is a proof of phi using the logical
axioms and premises in Sigma following the rules of inference
This is a mechanical process which can be visualized as a tree
Truth in the semantical side is based on Tarki's definition of
truth. Namely that something is true iff it is true in
all models. Here Sigma models phi means that in every structure
where Sigma is satisfied -- i.e. each sentence in Sigma happens
to be true-- phi is also satisfied.
For example, if we have an order relation in our vocabulary and
Sigma is the set of sentences expressing that the order relation is
transitive and irreflexive, then we can show that it is also assymetric.
So, any structure satisfying each of the two conditions in Sigma, which
happens in any irreflexive partially ordered set, such as a number line,
or a tree, or a lattice, will also satisfy phi.
Another way to see this, is that there is no structure in the
mathematical universe, which makes Sigma true but which makes phi false. It is
natural to wonder what is the relation between these two worlds.
In 1929, Godel proved that these two relations are equivalent
for First order logic. To understand this, we will have
to dive into the basics of mathematical logic.