On the one hand we have the syntax, which can be
seen as manipulations of symbols being governed by a special theorem
proving computer, which takes in axioms as input and outputs theorems.
Once it has proven a theorem, we can feed this
theorem back into it's inputs to prove more theorems.
If chi is such a theorem and Sigma is out set of
axioms then we denote this situation by this relation, which is read
as Sigma proves chi. The theory of a given set of axioms
is the set of all such theorems, which in our analogy is
the set of all possible outputs from our theorem proving computer.
On the other side we have the intuitive world of semantics, where
truth is based on Tarki's definition of truth, namely that something is
true if and only if it is true in all models. We
will now attempt to make this precise, which may be a bit
boring, but it leads us to interesting places.
Formally, a structure --which we denote which this fancy
M-- is given by this tuple of elements.
This is some arbitrary set, and denotes
the universe or domain of the structure.
And these are the interpretations of the symbols of the language.
In math there are certain symbols which are known as
the logical symbols which include variables, quantifiers, Boolean connectives --such
as conjunction, disjunction, implication and negation-- and brackets. For a
mathematician, these exist in the background world of logic.
Then there are certain symbols know as the non-logical symbols
which are the constants --like 0,1,e,pi etc., functions --such as
addition multiplication and relations--such as <, or the set theoretic
membership relation. These are the set of symbols specific to
a given mathematical theory. As we saw earlier, constants simply
get interpreted as certain elements of the domain.
The formal definition of the interpretations of function and relation symbols is a
bit strange at first, as they get interpreted as a sets of tuples
which satisfy a given relationship. For example, the less than relation would be
the set of all pairs of natural numbers (a,b) such that the interpretation
of a is less than the interpretation of b.
We could represent this on the number line by drawing every
possible arrow between nodes which is going to the right.
Earlier I said that function symbols can be
interpreted as computer programs, well, formally they will
be interpreted as a special type of relation.
For example the plus symbols will be interpreted as the set
of triples (a,b,c) such that a+b=c. They are special relations, because
we know that the output is uniquely determined by the inputs.