In this video series we will go deep into mathematical logic to
try and figure out what math is, and what it's limits are.
For much of history math was essentially geometry, in the sense that
everything we proved was grounded in some form of geometric intuition.
Its not hard to imagine triangles, squares and circles, and
as we start to study them, we can start to
notice certain patterns, find different ways classify the shapes and
we can find certain surprising relations between different shapes.
However, infinity is hiding even within a simple triangle, as was
shown by the pythagoreans that the square root of two --which
is the length of the long side of any unit right
angle triangle-- is incommensurable meaning that its decimal expansion is endless.
Allowing more abstract ideas into mathematics broadened the scope of math, and
made it more applicable in the real world. But this came at
the cost of making math harder to wrap our heads around.
For now I will just say that in the 1800's
mathematics had developed far beyond the intuitive realm of geometry.
However, math had branched out in so many different ways, that it
was hard to pin down what math was. This prompted people in
the 1800's to attempt to ground mathematics in the logic.
To understand this, let us return to the easy
stuff and consider 1+2=3. When viewed in one way,
this is just an arbitrary string of five symbols.
It get's its meaning when interpreted in a structure like the
natural number line, where the numbers get interpreted as we expect.
The plus sign can be interpreted as a function
--which we can see as a computer program-- which
takes in two inputs and has a well-defined output.
The equality symbol just checks that the two sides of the equation map to
this same element in the line, so we say that the equation holds.
Now, if we consider a more complicated equation such as Euler's
identity, we see that this equation is meaningless in the natural
number line, since the intended interpretations of each of the constants
involved do not exist in the natural number line.
To understand this equation, we require a more
complex structure known as the complex plane.
However, once we have done this, we can evaluate it
in the same way as 1+2=3. We just have map
the constants to their representations in the structure,
and then perform the complex exponentiations function, and we can observe
that the left side hand side evaluates to the same point
in the structure as the interpretation of the right hand side.
3 Blue 1 Brown made an excellent video explaining why
this equality holds --you can check that video out here--.
But from the point of view of a logician,
both of these formulas are the simplest possible. They
are at the bottom of the complexity hierarchy.
Using quantifiers, which are these symbols and
are read as for all, and exists,
We can create more complicated formulas using quantifiers. For example, consider this
equation, which states that the sum of the first n odd numbers
is equal to n-squared. Meaning that 1 plus 3 plus 5 plus
dot dot dot n-times, then it is equal to n squared.
This is some random pattern which one notices if one looks for
patterns in the natural numbers for long enough. We can convince ourselves
that it is true by going through each possible value of n.
Since one is equal to 1 squared.
1 plus 3 is equal to 2 squared,
1 plus 3 plus 5 is equal to 3 squared etc.
It seems to always hold, but how do we know that there is
not some weird number, just beyond our grasp which breaks this pattern?
Well, to evaluate a formula such as this
one, we use the principle of mathematical induction.
Meaning that we check if it holds for n equals 1,
and check that if it holds for k, then it holds for k plus 1.
This can be seen using dominoes.
I will now say, if we know that we will push the first domino over,
and we know that given any domino,
if it falls over, then the next domino is guaranteed to fall as well,
then we can conclude that every domino will
eventually fall, even if there are infinitely many.