We need to define axioms to determine
the behaviour of this edge relation E.
Without any axioms, every possible combination of points and all possible
arrows drawn between them is a model of our empty theory.
An axiom can be any FOL sentence.
For example, we can consider
this formula phi, expressing transitivity,
meaning that if there is some path between nodes,
then there is a direct path between these nodes.
Or this sentence psi expressing irreflexivity, which enforces that any
model of it must not contain any self-referential arrows.
We can combine the sentences, and consider the collection
of all structures which satisfy both phi and psi,
i.e. the collection of all transitive and irreflexive structures.
In general, given any collection of sentences Sigma, this is the
model set of Sigma, and it is the set of possible
structures which satisfy each of the sentences in Sigma.
Note that if Sigma contains an unsatisfiable sentence, such as x
is not equal to x, then Mod Sigma will be empty.
And the soundness of First order logic, tells us
that if our set of sentence Sigma is consistent...
then there is at least one model out
there which satisfies every formula in Sigma.
We see that this is based on a platonistic
vision of mathematics, where mathematical structures are pre-existing,
and we can characterize them using first order sentences.
If we start to study the general structure of
the models in Mod(), we might notice some things
in common to all of these structures.
For example we may notice that in none of them do we have aEb and bEa.
We can easily see why, since if we did have
such an edge in a transitive and irreflexive structure,
then by transitivity we should have a direct path a to a.
But then the structure is not irreflexive, a contradiction.
So, we see that adding this
sentence chi expressing assymetry, is redundant,
in the sense that Mod(phi,psi,chi) = Mod(phi,psi).
We denote this by  models chi.
Recall that the deductive completeness of our calculus gives
us a guarantee that there is a proof of
chi from the axioms using phi,psi as assumptions.
Moving back to the world of syntax, as mentioned earlier, this
can be seen as a computational process, where at first the
axioms are put in, and derive a new formula like chi.
Once we have derived chi, we can use
it to prove more theorems and so on.
In this scenario, we would say that phi and psi are axioms,
and the consequences of phi and psi are theorems.
The theory of  is the set of all such theorems.
And note that as a consequence of soundness, all of these
theorems are satisfied in every model which satisfy phi and psi.
I.e. each theorem is satisfied in every transitive and irreflexive
structure. So we can see that the theorems of a
given set of sentences Sigma are exactly the set of
sentences satisfied by every model of Sigma.