We need to define axioms to determine the behaviour of this edge
relation E. Without any axioms, every possible combination of points and all
possible arrows drawn between them is a model of our empty theory.
An axiom can be any First Order Logic sentence. For
example, we can consider this formula phi, expressing transitivity,
meaning that if there is some path between nodes,
then there is a direct path between these nodes.
Or this sentence psi expressing irreflexivity, which enforces that any
model of it must not contain any self-referential arrows.
We can combine the sentences, and consider the collection
of all structures which satisfy both phi and psi,
i.e. the collection of all transitive and irreflexive structures.
In general, given any collection of sentences Sigma, this is the
model set of Sigma, and it is the set of possible
structures which satisfy each of the sentences in Sigma.
Note that if Sigma contains an unsatisfiable sentence, such as x
does not equal x, then Mod Sigma will be empty.
And the soundness of First order logic, tells us that if our set
of sentences Sigma is consistent, meaning that one cannot prove phi and not
phi for any formula phi as hard as you try, then there is
at least one model out there which satisfies every formula in Sigma.
We see that this is based on a platonistic
vision of mathematics, where mathematical structures are pre-existing, and
we can characterize them using first order sentences.
If we start to study the general structure of
the models satisfying phi and psi, we might notice
some things in common to all of these structures.
For example we may notice that in none of them do we have aEb and bEa.
We can easily see why, since if we did have such
an edge in a transitive and irreflexive structure, then by transitivity
we should have a direct path from a to a.
But then the structure is not irreflexive, a contradiction.
So, we see that adding this sentence chi expressing
asymmetry, is redundant, in the sense that Mod(phi, psi,
chi) is exactly equal to Mod(phi, psi).
We denote this by saying the set phi, psi models chi.