A mathematical structure M is defined algebraically as follows.
There is a set M, called the domain of the structure.
So, again for the theory of arithmetic, this would just be the
set of natural numbers. For a graph this would be the set
of vertices, etc. This is the domain over which the quantifiers range.
So in arithmetic, when we say for all x there
exists a y such that x is less than y,
the quantifiers range over the natural numbers and this says
that for all numbers, there is a bigger number,
whereas in the theory of graphs, the quantifiers range over
the set of vertices in the graph, if we change
the less than relation to the graph edge relation, this
expresses that all vertices have an outgoing edge.
Then we have a set of constant symbols, function
symbols and relation symbols specific to this theory.
The bridge between the syntax and the semantics is
given by an interpretation function, which is a special
map, sending each symbol to its interpretation,
such that constant symbols are mapped to elements in the domain,
function symbols are mapped to functions in the structure,
and relation symbols to subsets of the domain.
Where functions can be seen as tuples, where inputs are mapped uniquely to
an output. For example, the addition function will map to the set of
all possible triples a, b, c, where a plus b equals c.
Similarly, relation symbols will be mapped to all tuples satisfying the
axioms imposed on the relation symbol. For example the less than
relation in the theory of arithmetic, will map to all pairs
a, b such that a is less than b.
This is a bit of a contrived map, but
this is our bridge between the mechanical world of
syntax, where the symbols have no inherent meaning, and
the intuitive world of semantics where mathematical structures exist.
Finally, we need a variable assignment, which will map the
set of free variables to specific elements in the domain.
To motivate this, we show how formulas with free variables,
serve a completely different purpose to formulas without free variables.
Where a free variable is one which is not bounded by
a quantifier. For example, there exists an x such that x
plus x equals y. Here x is bounded by the existential
quantifier and so it is not free, but y is free.
Formulas without free variables, such as 1 plus 1 equals 2, or for all
x there exists y where x is greater than y are known as sentences,
and they make a claims about the structure in question, which are either true
or false in the structure. Formulas with free variables, such as x is less
than y, or there exists an x such that x plus x equals y,
are sometimes true and sometimes false, depending on what x and y refer to.
Formulas with free variables are used for definitions.
For example, in the structure of the natural numbers, this formula defines the set
of even numbers, since it is true if and only if we instantiate y
by an even number. So, we can define E equals the set of y
such that there exists an x such that x plus x equals y.
So, a mathematical structure is defined as the pair M, Phi,
where M is as before, and Phi is a map from
the free variables in the formulas to elements in the domain.
Now we can define the satisfaction relation, which is
the definition of truth in the semantical world.
So, when we say 1 plus 2 equals 3, we check whether the terms
1 plus 2 and 3 evaluate to the same element in the structure.
On the right hand side, we simply map 3
to its interpretation, which is just the number 3.
On the left we have a function term, so we map the
components to their interpretations, and then evaluate the result of the function.
Similar for other atomic formulas, such as 2 plus 3 is less than
4 times 3. We evaluate the terms on each side, and check whether
the result exists in the subset of pairs of numbers in the relation.
Then, for boolean combinations, the definition of truth is given recursively as we
would expect. So phi and psi is true in a structure if and
only if both phi and psi individually are true in the structure.
For the quantifiers, an expression for all x phi x evaluates to true, if no
matter which value we choose for x, it turns out to be true. For example,
for all x, x plus 1 squared equals x squared plus 2x plus 1 is
true of all natural numbers, and so will be true in N.