When people think of math, they think of
equations such as 1 plus 2 equals 3,
or e to the pi i equals negative 1.
These equations get their meaning when we interpret them into a structure. Where
1 plus 2 equals 3 is understood based on the number line.
Where we interpret the numbers as we would expect, namely
as the first, second, and third elements after 0.
Since the addition function can be defined as a primitive recursive function,
we can think of the addition function as being a computer program
which takes in two inputs and gives a well-defined output.
So we map the symbol plus to represent this program...
and we feed in the interpretations of the 1 and 2 as input...
and map the output to a number on the line.
We see that in this case, the two sides of the
equation map to the same element in the structure, so we
see that indeed 1 plus 2 equals 3, a shocker.
Note that, the addition function can be seen more abstractly as a set
of triples. Imagine the set of all sets of three natural numbers.
This can be seen as every point in
a 3-D grid over the natural numbers.
For each point in this space, we can check
if the first two elements sum to the third.
If this happens, then we include this set
of triples into the interpretation of plus.
If they map to different values, they are excluded.
After repeating this process on all sets of triples, we obtain the
interpretation of the addition symbol plus M, which is just all numbers
a, b, c such that a plus b equals c.
So, we see that the plus function gives us a relation between
triples of natural numbers. So, the fact that 1 plus 2 equals
3, reveals some hidden relation between the numbers 1, 2, and 3.
Similar to how 2, 3 and 8 are related,
because 2 to the power of 3 equals 8.
So, we see that there is some structure, the number line,
which exists somewhere, and hidden within it are many relations between
its members which we can capture with certain equations.
Now, the second equation e to the pi i equals
negative 1 does not make sense in the number line,
as none of the constant symbols exist there.
To understand this equation, we need a more
sophisticated structure known as the complex plane.
Although this equation seems much more intimidating, evaluating it follows
the same general pattern. We just need to map each
of the constants to their interpretation in the structure.
And then carry out the function operations and check
if both sides map to the same element.
3 Blue 1 Brown made an excellent video explaining the
intuition behind why this equation holds. But for now, the
takeaway is that much of mathematics comes down to finding
hidden relations between elements in certain mathematical structures.
But what do we mean by a mathematical structure?
Formally a structure, which we denote by this
fancy M, is defined algebraically as this tuple:
Where the M is the domain, and these are
the interpretations of the symbols in the language.
Where the language contains a specific set of constants, which
are just specific elements of the domain, such as 0,
1, pi, e, function symbols, such as addition, exponentiation, and
relation symbols such as the less than symbol.
We just saw that binary functions, which just means that they take
in two inputs, can be represented as ternary relations, meaning relations between
three things, and where an n-ary relation, meaning it relates n-elements at
a time, are just subsets of M to the n.