When people think of math, they often think
of formulas such as 1+2=3 or e^pii=-1
But from a certain point of view, these are
just meaningless strings symbols. They get their meaning only
when they are interpreted into an appropriate structure.
For example, starting simple, 1 plus 2 equals
3 is understood based on the number line.
The numbers involved get interpreted as we would expect...
then we can interpret the plus symbol as a function
which takes in two inputs and has a well-defined output.
We see that the output of this function is the same as
the interpretation of the right-hand side, and so the equality holds.
Note that, the addition function can be seen more abstractly
as a set of triples. We can imagine considering the
set of all sets of three natural numbers.
Then we check if the first two sum to the third.
If this happens then we include this
set of triples into our addition set.
If they don't, we exclude them. So, the fact that 1 plus 2
equals 3, reveals some hidden relation between the numbers 1, 2, and 3.
Similarly to how 2, 3 and 8 are related,
because 2 to the power of 3 equals 8.
Now, more complicated equations, such as Euler's identity don't
make sense in the natural number line, since none
of the constants involved in the equation exist there.
To understand this equation, we require a more
complex structure known as the complex plane.
However, once we have done this, we can evaluate it in
essentially the same way as 1 plus 2 equals 3. We
just map the constants to their representations in the structure,
and then perform the complex exponentiation function, and we observe that
the left hand side evaluates to the same point in the
structure as the interpretation of the right hand side.
3 Blue 1 Brown made an excellent video explaining why
this equality holds, you can check that video out here.
But the takeaway is that mathematicians often have some structure in mind,
and they are trying to find the hidden relations between the elements
in this structure. Some of the relations are surprising, since e, pi,
i and negative 1 have very different definitions, so it's not obvious
a-priori that there would be any elegant relation between them. But once
we have defined the correct structure and the behaviour of complex exponentiation,
we can see why this equation holds.
But formulas such as these ones, are the simplest possible.
They simply exert a relation between certain elements.
Now, by adding quantifiers, which are these symbols,
we can express properties of every element in
a structure, even if that structure is infinite.
For example, consider this formula: for all x, the sum from i
equals 1 to x of 2i minus 1 equals x squared.
Which means that if we sum the first n
odd numbers, the result will be n squared.
This is true in the natural number line, but
to evaluate it, technically we would have to check
that it holds for every single natural number.
But how do we know that at some point just beyond our
reach there is not some weird number which breaks the pattern?
We prove such equations by induction. We show that it holds for
the base case of 1, and then show that if it holds
for some arbitrary number k, then it holds for k plus 1.
Don't worry about the details here, the point is
that by using quantifiers, and accepting the principle of
mathematical induction, a short string of symbols can tell
us something about every element in an infinite structure.
By the way, adding quantifiers to our logic, moves us up
from 0'th order logic, aka Propositional logic, into First Order Logic.
Propositional logic is too weak to define mathematical structures. For those
who are curious, there is also second order logic and even
higher-order logics, where we allow so-called higher order quantification, meaning that
we can iterate over subsets of the domain.
In FOL when we write for all x P x, we mean that every element
of the structure has the property P, whatever P is. In the natural number line,
this means that P of 0 holds, P of 1 holds and so on.
In SOL we write for all big X P of big X.
And this means that P holds for every subset of natural numbers.
This allows us more expressive power, but the notion of logical
validity becomes separated from our ability to prove statements. So first
order logic sits in a goldilocks zone where it is strong
enough to be able to define most of mathematics, and yet
not so strong that we lose control over it.
So to recap, in math we have certain formulas
which express relations between specific elements in the domain,
and we have other formulas which
can express properties about entire structures.
We can continue to generate increasingly powerful formulas, by alternating
quantifiers. This is given by the so-called arithmetic hierarchy.
At the base, we have the so-called Sigma 0 formulas, which
have no quantifiers. These are the simple equations like 1 plus
2 equals 3 and Euler's identity we saw earlier.
Next we have the Sigma 1 and the Pi 1
sentences, which include the existential and the universal formulas.
Where an existential formula is just one that starts with an existential
quantifier, such as exists y such that x plus x equals y.
And a universal formula starts with a universal quantifier
Moving up the hierarchy, we can obtain more
sophisticated formulas, which allow us to describe more
complicated structures by alternating the quantifiers.
The Pi 2 formulas are those which start with a for all
block and then an existential block, for example: for all x exists
y such that x is less than y. Which is true of
the natural numbers, as there are always larger numbers.
But if we switch the order of the quantifiers, we obtain the Sigma
2 sentences, which go exists then for all, and we obtain exists y
for all x, x is less than y, which is not true of
the natural numbers. Since a witness to this existential quantifier would be an
actually infinite number, as it would be greater than every natural number.
We can continue in this way. We move up
the hierarchy diagonally, by prepending the opposite quantifier to
the one which appears first in the lower level.
I will quickly note that we can divide the
set of formulas in two different types based on
whether a formula contains so-called free variables.
A sentence is a formula without any free variables, which include sentences
without any variables at all, such as 1 plus 2 equals 3,
or sentences in which all variables appear bound like this one.
Sentences make a claim which is either true
or false when interpreted into a structure.
Non-sentence formulas have free variables, such as exists y such that y plus
y equals x, where we see that there is no quantifier to bound
the occurrence of x, so we say that x appears free. Such formulas
are sometimes true and sometimes false depending on what the variables point to.
They are therefore not used to make claims about the properties within a
structure, instead they allow us to define certain sets.
Since exists y y plus y equals x is true in the natural
numbers if and only if the free variable x is instantiated by an
even number, right since if we try with the number 3 for example,
there is no natural number which can be added to itself to obtain
3. We can define the set E of all such x.
So, in this arithmetic hierarchy, we either have sentences which express
properties of a given structure or elements within it, or we
have formulas which allow us to define certain sets.
As we go up in this hierarchy, we can define more complicated
sets, and make more complicated claims about a structure. But what do
we mean by a mathematical structure in the first place?