Once we have fixed our vocabulary, we can define the well-formed
terms and well-formed formulas. This is somewhat similar to English.
If we image the set of all possible combinations
of letters in the alphabet, most will be meaningless.
However, some combinations of letters form words.
Here we define the terms recursively,
where in the base case we say that the set
of terms consists of: 1. All constants in the language,
and 2. All variables in the language.
Then if we have a function symbol F, which expects n-inputs, then given n
terms t_1 through t_n, the term Ft_1 through t_n is also a term.
So all of the following are examples
of terms in the language of arithmetic.
Note that terms without variables, which are known as closed
terms simply point to specific elements of the structure.
So in the theory of arithmetic, they simply point to numbers.
Once we have our terms, we can combine them
to create well-formed formulas. Similar to English, well-formed formulas
are special combinations of terms that are grammatically correct.
Again, these are defined recursively, where in the base case we have the
relation terms, of the form: R t_1 through t_n, where R is n-ary.
Note we are being general here, and most relations are binary. In
form, these are the same as the functional terms, but instead of
pointing to specific elements of the structure, they make a claim about
the structure, which may or may not be true.
For example, the following are atomic formulas in the theory of arithmetic: 1+1=3.
And 3 times 5 is less than 2 plus 8 times 12.
Then we can inductively define the non-atomic formulas using the Boolean
connectives and the quantifiers. So if phi and psi are terms,
then so is phi and psi,
so is for all x phi, etc.
Now we are ready to define what a mathematical structure is, and
how we construct a bridge between the worlds of syntax and semantics.