In this video series, we will go deep into mathematical logic
to figure out what math is and what its limits are.
For much of history, math was essentially geometry, in the
sense that everything we proved was grounded in geometric intuition.
It is not hard to imagine triangles, squares, and circles, and
as we study them, we discover hidden properties within these shapes.
The world of geometry feels natural and intuitive — yet
complexity hides even within a simple unit right triangle.
The length of its longest side is the square root of two,
which is irrational, meaning its decimal expansion is infinite and non-repeating.
As math developed, it became further abstracted from
our intuitions. With the development of calculus, the
concept of points at infinity became commonplace.
We cannot directly picture an infinite process, yet this
framework proved useful for describing the physical world.
In algebra, negative numbers and eventually
imaginary numbers became accepted tools.
All of this broadened the scope of math and made
it more powerful — but also harder to grasp intuitively.
And since math had branched into so many different areas, it
became difficult to say what math actually was. Analysis looked quite
different from group theory, which looked very different to number theory.
In the 19th and early 20th century,
mathematicians attempted to ground math in logic.
Frege observed that the act of doing mathematics involved
the manipulations of the same basic symbols: functions,
relations,
constants,
variables,
quantifiers,
and the boolean connectives of
conjunction, disjunction, implication, and negation.
This aligns with the syntactic, or formalist, view that math is
a game played with meaningless symbols according to fixed rules.
The opposing view is semantic: that there exist pre-existing
mathematical structures in some platonic world of forms,
which our formulas attempt to describe and categorize.