We can look at math from two
different points of view. Syntactically and Semantically.
The world of syntax is a formal and mechanical world
where truth is given by proofs in a formal calculus.
Which is just a specific set of axioms
written in a formal language, which can be combined
according to certain rules of inference to generate proofs.
The semantics is the intuitive world in which the symbols
of our logical language get interpreted into. Similar to how
English words are just words which describe things that actually
exist in the world. If viewed platonically, we can see
mathematical formulas as describing properties of pre-existing structures which enhabit
a perfect world of forms.
This platonistic view of math is not shared by everyone. Some
hold a formalist view of math, in which they ignore the
semantic side of math choosing instead to work entirely within the
confines of syntax. Others hold a constructivist view of math, where
we have to be able to construct or at least define
a mathematical object before we can say that it exists.
But the branch of mathematics which deals with the relation
between the syntax and the semantics --known as Model Theory--
makes the most sense when viewed from the platonic world.
There are different languages within which we can define our logic:
Propositional or 0th order logic,
FOL
and finally Higher OL's.
Of these FOL is used to build or define mathematics. This is because
FOL is strong enough to describe most mathematical structures well enough, and not
so strong that we can no longer define a complete and sound calculus
for it. We will see what this means later in this video.
But, we will start simple by
understanding the basic of propositional logic.