In this video series, we are going to go deep into mathematical logic
to try to figure out what math is, and where its limits are.
In the first video, we will cover syntax vs. semantics, define
what a formal proof is, and the definition of mathematical structures.
In the second video, we will cover basic set theory, since theories
are defined using sets, and yet sets are defined using a theory.
In the third video, we will cover Skolem's paradox, showing how
first order logic cannot fully capture or determine certain properties.
In the fourth video, we will cover the deductive completeness of
first order logic, providing a bridge between syntax and semantics.
In the fifth video, we will see the basics
of primitive recursion, decidability, and the Halting problem.
Finally, we will cover Godel's incompleteness
theorem and discuss its implications.
As a bonus video, we will cover non-classical logics, and
see how they give rise to different visions of mathematics.