It was Frege in the 19th century, who first realized
that mathematics involved manipulations involving a specific set of symbols.
These included the logical symbols such as the
boolean connectives: conjunction, disjunction, implication and negation:
The quantifiers forall and exists
The variables
And finally brackets
The non-logical symbols include the constants,
function symbols and relation symbols:
The reason for the distinction, is that the non-logical symbols are
specific to a given theory. So, if we just restrict our
attention to the logical symbols, we are in the domain of
logic, since whatever we prove holds in all possible theories.
Now, if we restrict ourselves further, omitting the
quantifiers, then we are in the domain of
Propositional logic, also known as 0th order logic.
In fact we can prove that if we only use
implies and negation we don't lose any expressive power.
Here we can write down a propositional sentence phi
by combining propositional variables according to the connectives.
In classical logic, to check if phi is true, we can
simply create the truth table and check if there is a
satisfying assignment, that is, a row where our formulas are 1.
We can check if it is valid, by checking if all
of the rows evaluate to 1. This truth table can be
seen as a model in which this sentence holds.
In classical logic, this truth assignment is black and white. Display the truth table
for phi implies psi, a 2 by 2 matrix with 1s and 0s.
We can generalize to create a many-valued logic, where the
concept of truth is stretched out over an arbitrary number.
Extend the matrix one box at a time.
It can even be a real number between 0 and 1. Now make
there be an open interval and display something resembling a color selection window.