In this video series we will go deep into mathematical logic to
try and figure out what math is, and what it's limits are.
For much of history math was essentially geometry, in the sense that
everything we proved was grounded in some form of geometric intuition.
Its not hard to imagine triangles, squares and circles, and as
we start to study them, we can start to notice certain
patterns, find different ways classify the shapes and we can find
certain surprising relations between different shapes. For example,
we can prove that the sum of the inner angles of any triangle
is exactly 180 degrees by drawing a parallel line at its top vertex.
The world of geometry is natural and intuitive. However, as
math developed, it has become further abstracted from our intuitions.
By allowing more abstract ideas --such as infinity methods-- into mathematics
allows us to broaden the mathematical universe but it comes at
the cost of making math harder to wrap our heads around.
I will soon make a whole video on the history of
math. For now I will just say that in the 1800's
mathematics had developed far beyond the intuitive realm of geometry.
Calculus had been developed which accepted the idea
of points at infinity, algebra had developed significantly,
and many had started to accept the existence
of imaginary numbers as legitimate mathematical objects.
However, math had branched out in so many different ways
that there was no longer a common foundation for mathematics.
In the 1800's people --such as Frege, Peano Russell and
others-- started to ground mathematics in the logic.
To understand this, let us return to the easy stuff and
consider 1 plus 2 equals 3. When viewed in one way,
this is just an arbitrary string of five symbols.
It get's its meaning when interpreted in a structure like the
natural number line, where the numbers get interpreted as we expect.
The plus sign can be interpreted as a function
--which we can see as a computer program-- which
takes in two inputs and has a well-defined output.
The equality symbol just checks that the two sides of the equation map to
this same element in the line, so we say that the equation holds.
Now, if we consider a more complicated equation such as Euler's
identity, we see that this equation is meaningless in the natural
number line, since the intended interpretations of each of the constants
involved do not exist in the natural number line.
To understand this equation, we require a more
complex structure known as the complex plane.
However, once we have done this, we can evaluate it in
the same way as 1 plus 2 equals 3. We just
have map the constants to their representations in the structure,
and then perform the complex exponentiations function, and we can observe
that the left side hand side evaluates to the same point
in the structure as the interpretation of the right hand side.
3 Blue 1 Brown made an excellent video explaining why
this equality holds --you can check that video out here--.
But from the point of view of a logician,
both of these formulas are the simplest possible. They
are at the bottom of the complexity hierarchy.
We can create more complicated formulas using quantifiers. For example,
consider this equation, which states that the sum of the
first n odd numbers is equal to n-squared.
Meaning that 1 plus 3 plus 5 plus dot dot dot n-times, then
it is equal to n squared. This is some random pattern which one
notices if one looks for patterns in the natural numbers for long enough.
We can convince ourselves that it is true
by going through each possible value of n.
Since one is equal to 1 square.
1 plus 3 is equal to 2 squared,
1 plus 3 plus 5 is equal to 3 squared etc.
It seems to always hold, but how do we know that there is
not some weird number, just beyond our grasp which breaks this pattern?
Well, to evaluate a formula such as this one, we use the principle
of mathematical induction, which just means that we check that it holds for
n equals 1, and check that if it holds for n equals k,
then it also applies to n equals k plus 1.
This can be seen using dominoes, if we know that we will
push the first domino, and we know that once any domino falls,
it will knock over the next domino, then we know that every
domino will eventually fall, even if there are infinitely many of them.
So, we see that by adding quantifiers into our logic, and by
accepting mathematical induction, we can prove things about every element in an
infinite structure, using finitely many symbols. But what do we mean by
prove? There turn out to be two very different ways of defining
a mathematical proof --and therefore of defining mathematical truth-- and the relationship
between them is at the heart of mathematical logic.