The syntactical world is governed by a deductive calculus,
which we can picture as a theorem-proving computer.
Feed it a set of axioms as input, and it
will output their logical consequences — which we call theorems.
The symbols of this system divide into logical and
non-logical, and the axioms divide the same way.
The logical axioms are like the operating system running in the
background of all mathematics, determining how the logical symbols behave.
Different choices of logical axioms may give different logics —
in this series we will work with classical first-order logic,
and I will dedicate a later video to non-classical logics.
On top of this logical foundation, different fields of
mathematics introduce their own constants, functions, and relations, along
with their own axioms, giving rise to different theories
like number theory, field theory, and group theory.
Formally, a theory is the set of all consequences of its axioms
— i.e. everything the theorem-proving computer can output from those inputs.
So, on the syntactic side, mathematic truth
means provability in a formal calculus.
On the semantic side, truth is given by Tarski's definition: a
sentence is true if and only if it holds in every
model. Let us make this precise — it may feel technical
for a moment, but it leads somewhere interesting.
Formally, a structure — which we denote with the symbol M —
is given by a tuple consisting of a domain, or universe, together
with interpretations of the constants, functions, and relations in the language.
To define the natural numbers with addition and multiplication, for
instance, we need at least the symbols zero, one, the
addition function, the multiplication function, and the less-than relation.
We interpret zero and one as expected.
Functions act like computer programs: they take
inputs and produce a uniquely determined output.
Relations are slightly more abstract — formally, the less-than
relation is interpreted as the set of all pairs
(a, b) such that a is less than b.
Note that functions are just special relations where
the output is uniquely determined by the inputs.
So the successor function would map to the set of all pair
of numbers such that the second is one greater than the first.
And the addition function is formally the set of all triples
(a, b, c) such that a plus b equals c.
To evaluate a simple equation like one plus two
equals three, we map the constants as expected
and then check whether the resulting
triple belongs to the addition relation.