The syntax of classical propositional logic is given by a calculus. There
are many calculi which turn out to be equivalent, but each has
a set of axioms, which are just some logically valid formulas...
...and rules of inference, which allow us to derive new
formulas from a set of premises while preserving truth.
The most concise calculus is the Hilbert style calculus, which has
the following 3 axioms, and the only rule of inference is
Modus Ponens, which says that if you have phi and you
have phi implies psi, then you can conclude psi.
These axioms seem random at first, and you may notice that
conjunction and disjunction do not appear, but one can prove that
they are both necessary and sufficient for propositional logic.
Once we have our calculus, we can start to construct proofs.
We can visualize proofs as trees, where the leaves are axioms,
and we combine nodes using our rule of inference.
Proofs can also be seen as computer programs. Where the axioms can be
used as inputs, and modus ponens is seen as running a given program.
Since phi implies psi can be interpreted as a computer
program which if given phi as input, can output psi.
So, an application of Modus Ponens is akin to running a computer
program. The complexity, and therefore power, comes from the fact that the
input formula phi, can be seen as a program itself.
So we can pass programs as input to other programs. I
will cover this in more detail in a later video, but
for now just know that the world of syntax deals with
formal proofs, and proofs can be carried out by computers.
There are two main questions we can ask about our calculus.
The first is whether we can trust it. Meaning if we prove something
in our calculus, how do we know that it is really true?
In propositional logic this is easy to check,
since each of the axioms is logically valid...
...again this means that each row in their truth table evaluates to 1.
And clearly Modus Ponens preserves truth. So whatever we prove will
be logically valid. This means that our calculus is sound.
The second question is whether this list
is sufficient to prove all valid statements?
So, if we come across some arbitrary formula phi, and we
check the truth table, and see that all rows evaluate to
1, can we guarantee that there is a proof of phi?
Perhaps there is some valid statement out there which no matter
how hard we try, we cannot prove. Perhaps we need to
add more axioms? This is the question of completeness.
It turns out that this set of axioms is complete and we
will see a stronger version of this in the fourth video.
So, this simple calculus can only prove logically valid
statements, and it can prove all logically valid statements.