To understand the relation between these two worlds,
let's first consider the simple world of classical
propositional logic, also known as 0th order logic.
Here we have a set of propositional variables,
which can either be true or false.
These serve as the atoms of our logic, which
we can combine using the Boolean connectives of conjunction,
disjunction, implication and negation to form proposition formulas.
The connectives are governed by truth tables, where conjunction,
disjunction, and negation are as we would expect.
In classical logic, implication is equivalent to 'not p or q', meaning that p
implies q is true either if p is false, or q is true.
Note that there are non-classical logics which interpret these symbols differently,
especially implication and negation. We will cover this in the bonus
video at the end, for now we stick to classical logic.
So, given an arbitrary propositional formula, like this one,
we can easily evaluate it using a truth table.
Meaning that we list every possible combination of 0 and
1 for the propositional variables involved in the formula, and
then compute the output using the rules of the connectives.
If all rows evaluate to 1, as is the case with
this formula, then we say that the formula is logically valid.
If all rows evaluate to 0, then
we say that the formula is unsatisfiable.
And if at least one row is true, then we say that it is satisfiable.
We see that each row in the truth table represents
a specific interpretation of the propositional variables. So each row
can be seen as a possible world or interpretation.