It was Frege in the 1800's who realized that doing
mathematics involved manipulations of the following set of symbols:
Constant symbols, such as numbers like 0, 1,
e, or pi, or any other special element.
Function symbols, such as addition or multiplication.
Relation symbols, such as less than or in.
Variables, quantifiers, brackets, and the Boolean connectives.
The Boolean connectives can be represented
by truth tables or logic gates.
Importantly, in classical logic, a implies b
is equivalent to not a or b
and is given by this truth table.
This is not the case in intuitionistic logic for example.
But for now we stick to classical logic, and soon
I will make a video on non-classical logics. So all
of math comes down to manipulation of these symbols.
We can divide these symbols into two groups, the logical and non-logical
symbols. The logical symbols are common to all first order theories, and
so proofs only involving the logical symbols apply to all possible structures.
The non-logical symbols are specific to a given theory.
For example if we are working with the theory of arithmetic,
we would need the constant 0,
the successor function,
the addition or multiplication function,
and perhaps the order relation.
If we work with the theory of graphs,
we only need a single binary relation E,