In some sense the goal of mathematics is
to add enough axioms such that there is
exactly one structure which satisfies them.
In this case, the theory of Sigma is a perfect description of
the structure, it contains everything we could possibly say about the structure
in first order logic in the language of the structure.
If a theory has a finite model, then there is
a single sentence phi which fully characterizes the theory, and
therefore there is exactly one model up to isomorphism.
However, in the third video, we will see why
this is impossible for a theory with infinite models.
But we can still achieve something weaker, namely that all
models of our set Sigma satisfy the same sentences.
You may ask how we can know that two models M and N are
actually different if they satisfy the same sentences. Again, we will see this in
the third video, but for now just know that this has to do with
the inability of First Order Logic to deal with the complexities of infinity.
However, if we have such a set Sigma, then we cannot
differentiate any of its models using a single first order sentence.
So, given any sentence alpha we can write, either every
model satisfies it, or every model satisfies its negation.
In this case we say that the theory is complete.
Syntactically, completeness means that the theory is maximally consistent, in
the sense that for every formula alpha, either alpha is
in Sigma, or not alpha is in Sigma.
Thus, it decides everything that it possibly can.
If we added even a single new formula alpha to a complete theory,
it would then become inconsistent, and it would therefore have no models.