Returning to our example of Sigma equals phi, psi, we
can easily see that this set is not complete.
We see that the natural number line is a model of
Sigma where E is interpreted as the less than relation.
Since for all numbers x, y, z, if x is less than y
and y is less than z, then x is less than z,
and no number is less than itself.
However, a tree is also a model of Sigma
where we interpret E based on the direct-extension relation.
Since if a extends b, and b extends c, then a must
extend c. And no node is a direct extension of itself.
And clearly, we can find a sentence chi to
differentiate between a tree and a number line. For
example, we could add this sentence, expressing totality, meaning
that all elements are related by the edge relation.
We see that our tree is not a model of this, since two
different elements at the same level are not comparable by the extension relation.
So, we could add chi as another axiom to our set Sigma.
So Sigma now contains phi, psi, chi, and Mod
Sigma is the set of linearly ordered sets.
However, the theory of Sigma is still not complete,
since for example both the natural numbers and the
rational numbers satisfy these axioms under the less than
relation, and we can differentiate the rational numbers from
the natural numbers by this sentence theta expressing density.
Meaning that for all x, y, if x is less than y, then there exists
a z such that x is less than z and z is less than y.
This is not true of the natural numbers, as there is
no natural number in between 0 and 1 for example.
However, given any fractional number, we can
always find a number in between it.
If we add theta to our set of axioms Sigma,
and we add two more axioms expressing that there are
no endpoints, then we get the theory of DLOWE.
In 1895 Georg Cantor proved that all countable
dense linear orderings without endpoints are isomorphic,
which technically just means that there is an order
preserving map between them, but essentially means that there
is a unique countable set which satisfies this set
of axioms, and this set is the rational numbers.
So, this set of axioms here, is a close
approximation of the structure of the fractional number line.
However, it is not perfect as the real
number line also satisfies the DLOWE axioms.
But this set of axioms is as good as we can hope
to do: Sigma is a complete axiomatization of the theory of DLOWE.